A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21 FA293
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
1926-1933
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman
Harkness, Edward Stephen
Harkness, Charles W.
Harkness, Anna M. Richardson
Commonwealth Fund
FA293
0.69 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents note
The Commonwealth Fund's association with the Institute for Child Guidance stems from a revision in the Fund's Program for the Prevention of Delinquency. The Delinquency Program was drafted during the summer and early fall of 1921, with the CF Board adopting the program in November of that year. Actual wok was not begun until the spring of 1922. The forerunner of the Institute for Child Guidance, The Bureau of Children's Guidance officially opened on February 1, 1922, but was not fully active until autumn of that year.
The five year period of the Delinquency Program expired in the spring of 1927. Already in early 1926, a revised program had been proposed. The Bureau of Children's Guidance closed June 30, 1927, and The Institute for Child Guidance opened in New York City on July 1, 1927. This new Institute, incorporated December 29, 1926, was affiliated with the New York School of Social Work and the Smith College School for Social Work in regards to the training of psychiatric social workers; and with the National Committee for Mental Hygiene in conjunction with the training of psychiatrists and graduate psychologists in practical child guidance work.
Both the administration and budget of the Institute were controlled by the Board of Directors of the Commonwealth Fund. The nine member Administrative Board of the Institute was appointed by the CF Board of Directors, which retained the right to terminate any appointment at its discretion. Barry C. Smith, Director of the CF, was named Chairman; Porter R. Lee, Director of the New York School for Social Work became treasurer. Other board members included Everett Kimball, Director of Smith College School for Social Work, Frankwood E. Williams, Medical Director of the National Committee for Mental Hygiene, Mildred C. Scoville, Executive Assistant of the CF, and Barbara S. Quin, also of the Commonwealth Fund.
Lawson G. Lowrey served as Director of the Institute, with David M. Levy as chief of staff, and Christine C. Robb as chief of social services. The initial yearly budget was approximately $160,000. Although the Institute officially closed its doors on June 30, 1933, the Bank of United States, which underwent liquidation at the same time, owed the organization over $20,000. Consequently, the Institute's certificate of incorporation was kept active. The bank's account with the Institute was fully settled in 1944, but the charter was not dissolved until 1951, when the Secretary of State of New York did so.
The majority of the Institute's surviving records consist of financial statements, audits and correspondence relating to fiscal or budget matters. The minutes of the Institute detail the activities of the Board of Directors, the incorporators, the annual corporation meetings, and the committee dividing the assets of the Institute. In late 1937 the Commonwealth Fund decided that all case files pertaining to the treatment of children at the Institute should be destroyed. Therefore, in February of 1938 these records, as well as the index to these cases, were burned. Other folders in this series contain sensitive material.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Mental health; Medical research; Medicine, Rural; Legal research; Medical education; Law; Legal issues; Education, Rural; Hygiene; Child psychology; Child welfare; New York (N.Y.); Child mental health; War relief; Public welfare; United States; New York (State); Public health; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Columbia University; Yale University; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Social Science Research Council; Harkness, Charles W.; Harvard University; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Commonwealth Fund
- Case Files - Access Regulations and Destruction of Files, 1929-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restricted - Confidential material. Requires prior archival review.
- Financial Records - Accounting Correspondence, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Financial Records - Accounting Correspondence, 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Financial Records - Accounts and Expenditures, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Financial Records - Accounts and Expenditures, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Financial Records - Accounts and Expenditures, January-December, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Financial Records - Accounts and Expenditures, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Financial Records - Audits, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Financial Records - Audits, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial Records - Bank of United States - Liquidation, 1930-1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial Records - Budget/Budget Correspondence, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Financial Records - Budget/Budget Correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Financial Records - Fellowship Accounts, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Financial Records - Income Tax, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Financial Records - New York Trust Company Account, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Financial Records - Personnel Bonuses, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Restricted - Confidential material.
- Financial Records - Treasurer's Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Financial Records - Treasurer's Correspondence, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Financial Records - Treasurer's Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Financial Records - Treasurer's Correspondence, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1927-1933 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Incorporation (By-laws, Certificate and Correspondence), 1926-1932 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Incorporation (Dissolution), 1933-1951 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Minutes, 1927-1933 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Property Inventories, 1927-1933 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Property Inventories, 1927-1933 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Property Inventories - Correspondence Concerning the Distribution of Assets, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 27)